Contact

Phone: 087 1211 867 Location: Ireland

Email:

oliverjnorton@gmail.com **Websites:**

- Portfolio
- GitHub
- LinkedIn

Skills

Programming

- Python
- SQL
- R

Data Visualisation

- Power BI
- Tableau
- Excel
- matplotlib
- Plotly

Data Science Libraries

- PyTorch
- · scikit-learn
- BERT
- XGBoost
- LightGBM
- Pandas
- NumPy
- Prophet
- BeautifulSoup

Data Engineering, Data Warehousing & Cloud Services

- Azure
- Docker
- Apache Kafka
- PostgreSQL
- DuckDB
- SQLite
- DBT
- Ucloud

Oliver Norton

With a master's in Social Data Science, experience as a Data Scientist, and a multitude of projects, I have the skills needed to excel in your team. I've honed my ability to communicate with non-technical stakeholders, and work as part of a team to deliver valuable business impact. For examples of my expertise, see my GitHub and website.

Experience

Feb 2023 - Jan 2024, Junior Data Scientist, Meltwater (Paris, France)

- Developed predictive time series models with Python Prophet to forecast demand for food ingredients in a €150,000 client project
- Performed in-depth analysis, created data visualisation dashboards and automated reporting, saving over 450 billable hours for colleagues
- Communicated clearly between cross-functional teams, and coordinated with non-technical stakeholders to provide data-driven insights
- Engineered Python scripts for ETL processes, leveraged data platform API framework, and managed Linux virtual machines (VMs)

Sep 2021 - Jun 2022, Administrative Assistant, Copenhagen University

- Maintained a research centre's website using HTML and a CMS, ensuring quality of content and structure
- Related with both technical staff scientists and the non-technical public, supporting scientific communication activities

Education

2021-2024, MSc in Social Data Science, University of Copenhagen

• Grade Average: 9.5/12 with grade 12/12 in master's thesis

2022, Academic Exchange, Sorbonne University

 Audited data science courses including: Probabilistic and Statistical Models and Algorithms for IT, Complexity, Databases, Networking

2017-2021, BA in Business, Economic & Social Studies, Trinity College Dublin

• Grade Average: 70% (First Class Honours)

2019-2020, Academic Exchange, UNSW Sydney

Projects

Fraud detection ML model with a large dataset using LightGBM

Dec 2024 | Data Science | View project on: Website, GitHub

- Developed a fraud detection model using Python package LightGBM, achieving ROC AUC of 0.932, and deployed using Kafka
- Conducted feature engineering, data wrangling, Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA), addressing class imbalance and data quality issues
- Applied gradient boosting and encoding to optimise model performance

Data pipeline and automation applied to energy data

Jul 2024 | Data Engineering | View project on: Website

- Designed and implemented robust data pipelines with ETL -like data process, using DBT, Docker, Python, Bash and Git
- Manipulated raw data and created models using SQL
- Implemented rigorous testing and quality checks to ensure data integrity
- Visualised data with Tableau and PowerBI dashboards to derive insights

Additional Skills

Development Tools

- Git
- JavaScript
- Confluence
- Jira
- Bash
- Linux

Other Tools

- Jupyter
- Google Data Studio

Languages

- English (Native)
- French (Fluent)
- Spanish (Inter.)
- Danish (Basic)

Projects (Continued)

Azure-based cloud architecture design for a carpooling company

Jun 2024 | Cloud Computing | View project on: Website

- In 72 hours, designed a data software architecture for client interested in migrating from an on-premise solution to the Cloud
- Security focused design including Identity and Access Management (IAM), encryption of data at rest/in transit and the Zero-Trust model
- Conducted a thorough risk-benefit analysis of cloud architecture, resulting in a design that enhanced data protection and compliance

Quantifying polarisation using networks and text data (Master's thesis)

Sep 2023 - Jan 2024 | Network Science | View on: Website

- Developed a novel multi-dimensional approach to quantify political polarisation, adhering to data governance standards
- Created a machine learning (ML) model (cross-validated Lasso regression)
- Utlised a cloud environment to access virtual machines (VM), execute code and run models

Investigating polarisation in Reddit Communities

Apr - May 2023 | Data Science

- Collected and cleaned over 50 GB of semi-structured Reddit data using a REST API (& Web scraping) for in-depth analysis
- Trained a multi-label sentiment classification model to categorise users

Analysing climate discourse with Natural Language Processing (NLP)

May - Jun 2022 | Data Science | Visualisation on: Website

- Analysed Twitter API text data, focusing on sentiment and discourse
- Developed ML classification models and used LDA topic modelling to identify key themes and trends in the conversation
- Visualised a retweet network employing community detection algorithms

Professional Development & Certifications

- AZ-900: Microsoft Azure Fundamentals Certification (In Progress)
- Intermediate JavaScript, Codecademy (In Progress)
- Introduction to JavaScript, Codecademy (Complete)
- Google Analytics Individual Qualification, Codecademy (Complete)
- Marketing Analytics Nanodegree, Udacity (Complete)

Personal Achievements

- Cycled over 4000 kilometres from Morocco to England at age 19
- Mastered French as a native English speaker
- · Lived in 7 countries and travelled to over 35
- Climbed the highest mountains in 5 countries: (Morocco 3400m, Zimbabwe 2592m, UK 1345m, and Ireland 1039m)